<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The honour of the cloathworking trade: Or, The pleasant and famous history of Thomas of Reading; and other worthy clothiers of the west and north of England. : Setting forth their merriments, great riches, hospitality to the poor, the favour they gained with their prince, and the privileges granted them. With the unfortunate loves of the Earl of Salisbury's fair daughter, and the renowned Duke of Normandy. The Woful death of Thomas of Reading, murthered by his host; and other matters. Also pleasant songs.</title>
            <author>Deloney, Thomas, 1543?-1600.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82329</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D955A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R174583</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45578321</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45578321</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172254</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82329)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172254)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2621:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The honour of the cloathworking trade: Or, The pleasant and famous history of Thomas of Reading; and other worthy clothiers of the west and north of England. : Setting forth their merriments, great riches, hospitality to the poor, the favour they gained with their prince, and the privileges granted them. With the unfortunate loves of the Earl of Salisbury's fair daughter, and the renowned Duke of Normandy. The Woful death of Thomas of Reading, murthered by his host; and other matters. Also pleasant songs.</title>
                  <author>Deloney, Thomas, 1543?-1600.</author>
                  <author>Clothworkers' Company (London, England)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2, [22] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Deacon, at the Angel in Gilt-spur-street, without Newgate.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[ca. 1680]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Humbly dedicated to the worshipful company of cloathworkers."</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English literature --  Early modern, 1500-1700.</term>
               <term>Clothing trade --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172254:1"/>
            <p>The Honour of the <hi>Cloathworking</hi> Trade: OR, THE Pleaſant and Famous Hiſtory OF <hi>Thomas of Reading:</hi> And other Worthy CLOTHIERS of the <hi>Weſt</hi> and <hi>North</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Setting forth their Merriments, Great Riches, Hoſpitality to the Poor, the Favour they gained with their Prince, and the Privileges granted them. With the Unfortunate Loves of the Earl of <hi>Salisbury</hi>'s fair Daughter, and the Renowned Duke of <hi>Normandy.</hi> The woful Death of <hi>Thomas of Reading,</hi> mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by his Hoſt; and other Matters. Alſo pleaſant SONGS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Humbly Dedicated to the Worſhipful Company of</hi> Cloathworkers.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut of three horsemen and merchants with carts</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed for <hi>J. Deacon,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Gilt-ſpur-ſtreet,</hi> without <hi>Newgate.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:172254:2"/>
            <head>The Honour of the <hi>Cloathworking</hi> Trade: OR, THE Pleaſant Hiſtory of <hi>Thomas of Reading,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I How in the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, <hi>Thomas of Reading,</hi> and many other honeſt wealthy Clothiers flouriſhed in the VVeſt and North. How in their way to <hi>London,</hi> the King met their great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of VVains that ſtopped him; and upon the Speech of a VVain-driver, made a Law againſt treading down and ſpoiling the Corn. How <hi>Thomas of Reading</hi> made a Requeſt to him, and his Anſwer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHen <hi>VVilliam Rufus</hi> who ſucceeded <hi>VVilliam the Conqueror</hi> in the Engliſh Throne, was killed as he hunted in <hi>New For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt,</hi> by an Arrow ſhot by <hi>Tyril,</hi> one of his Courtiers, which aimed at a Deer, and glancing on a Tree, gave the King his mortal Wound in the Side; his Brother <hi>Henry,</hi> ſirnamed from his great Learning and Wiſdom <hi>Beau Clark,</hi> or fine Scholar, winding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by great Gifts and Promiſes into the Affections of the Engliſh and Norman Nobility, got himſelf crowned King, whilſt his eldeſt Brother <hi>Robert,</hi> to whom the Conqueror had left the Dukedome of <hi>Normandy,</hi> was warring againſt the Turks and Sarazens in the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> and by his Valour won <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> of which City and the whole Country of <hi>Paleſtine</hi> the Chriſtian Princes would have crowned him King; but he refuſed it, and returning home to lay claim to <hi>England,</hi> a miſerable Fate or Misfortune befel him, as will appear in this Hiſtory in due place.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Henry,</hi> called King <hi>Henry the Firſt,</hi> the better to ſupport him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the Throne, made many good Laws, confirmed the great Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Nation, and did ſuch things as made Trade encreaſe, and his Subjects flouriſh. He inſtituted the High Court of Parliament, which has ever ſince continued, to the great good of the Commonwealth. In his Reign the Cloathing Trade very much encreaſed, and our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants brought home great Wealth for Engliſh Cloth, it being highly valued and prized in all Countries; ſo that the younger Sons of Knights and Gentlemen to whom their Fathers could leave no Lands, were preferred to be Cloathiers, and in Riches often exceeded their elder Brothers: And among the Eminenteſt for Wealth and Good Breeding,
<pb facs="tcp:172254:2"/> of this Calling, were in thoſe Days <hi>Thomas Cole,</hi> commonly called <hi>Thomas of Reading,</hi> as there born, and keeping his Cloth Manufacture, it being a very fair Town in <hi>Barkſhire; Grey</hi> of <hi>Glouceſter, Sutton</hi> of <hi>Salisbury, Fitzallen</hi> of <hi>VVorceſter</hi> commonly called <hi>VVilliam</hi> of <hi>VVorceſter, Thomas Dove</hi> of <hi>Exeter</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire, Simon</hi> of <hi>Southam;</hi> of whoſe Induſtry and Riches, and the great Number of poor People they employed daily, King <hi>Henry</hi> hearing, ſtiled them <hi>The Six VVorthy Yeomen of the VVeſt,</hi> and that Epithete they carried to their Graves.</p>
               <p>Beſides theſe there were others in the North who drove the ſame Trade, and did a great deal of good in the Land, <hi>viz Cuthbert of Kendale, Hodgkins</hi> of <hi>Hallyfax,</hi> and <hi>Martin Bryer</hi> of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> each of theſe kept at leaſt Two hundred Servants at work, <hi>viz.</hi> Weavers, Fullers, Dyers, Carders, Spinners, Sheermen, Wool-pickers, Rowers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> killing each in his Houſe two fat Oxen, beſide a great many Sheep, Swine, and the like, for the well feeding their Families; ſo that in Houſe-keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they outdid the beſt Gentlemen in the Counties where they lived; and theſe, to hold the better Correſpondency and ſettle the Prices of the Cloth, made an Agreement, under a Penalty of forfeiting 20 Pounds, to meet every <hi>VVhitſontide</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> and had their Warehouſe at <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard's-Hall,</hi> which was then an Inn, and ſo named from a huge mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Fellow that kept it, Nine Foot high, with Hands like Shoulders of Mutton.</p>
               <p>As they were on their way, their Wains laden with Cloth paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and made a Train like a huge Caravan, or the Baggage of a marching Army, ſtill encreaſing as the firſt called the next in the way, and ſo to the laſt, which was <hi>Thomas of Reading,</hi> who having highly feaſted them, ſet out with the reſt, his Wains going foremoſt, and being moſt in number; when ſo it happened, that the King, with the Prince his Son, and divers of his Nobility, were taking a Progreſs into <hi>VVales,</hi> to quiet the Welſh, who upon hearing that <hi>Robert</hi> Duke of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy</hi> was arming to invade <hi>England,</hi> began to riſe in tumults, and making Inroads, did much Miſchief to the Engliſh on the Borders. He no ſooner perceived this great Train of Wains that reached over Hills and Valleys many Miles, but he began to wonder what it ſhould mean, thinking that ſome great Army was behind, and theſe as the Vauntguard were laden with Proviſion and Ammunition. Some of the timerous Nobles perſwaded him not to advance, for fear of an Ambuſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they ſuppoſed theſe were ſent before to train him into, and ſo to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize and make his Royal Perſon a Priſoner; but he being of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Courage, reſolved to paſs on, and meeting the foreſmoſt at the coming out of a narrow Lane, then ſome Miles long, (for ſince the ways have been alter'd,) he demanded what they were, and who they belonged
<pb facs="tcp:172254:3"/> to? The Drivers anſwered, To <hi>Cole</hi> of <hi>Reading,</hi> and that they were Laden to <hi>London</hi> with Woollen Cloath, all his own Manufacture, and ſo they anſwered, till Fifty were paſſed; then others came on, and every one as they paſſed declared who they belonged to, which made the King wonder <hi>England</hi> ſhould abound with ſuch Wealthy People, which he little thought before it had done; yet vexed to be delayed, for the Lane being very narrow, he was forced to ſtay two or thee hours before they all paſſed by, when one of the Drivers, not knowing him to be the King, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving him to frown, ſaid bluntly, Good Fellow, what, art thou in haſt? Pray ſtay, and let your Betters be ſerved before you; you are, I ſuppoſe, ſome Country 'Squire going a Hunting, to ſpoil poor People's Corn, and a fine paſs they are brought to; I hope, e'er long, the King's Grace will be informed of it, and Puniſh ſuch Knaves as trample down the Bread the Poor ſhould eat; and ſo paſſed by, without ſtaying for a Reply. But theſe Words thrown out by the Country Fellow, did afterwards a great deal of good to the Nation; for the King, upon his Return, made a Law to limit the times of Hunting and Hawking, under great Penalties, and that ſuch Exerciſes ſhould be forborn, till the Corn was off the Ground, that it might not be ſpoiled or waſted, for the pleaſure of any, were he never ſo Rich or Noble; and this in a good meaſure has held ever ſince; for before, the Noblemen and Gentlemen, not regarding the meaner ſort, trampled down their Fields at pleaſure, and procured them to be puniſheed as Mutiniers, when they fought Redreſs.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of single horseman</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of two horsemen</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:172254:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>The Wains being all paſſed, and the way clear, the King rid on with his ſlender Train, and at the other end of the Lane met the Iolly Clothiers; <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Reading</hi> knew him, as ſerving the Court with Cloath, and informed the reſt it was the King; whereupon inſtantly alight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they tyed their Horſes to a Hawthorn-buſh, and kneeling, threw up their Caps, crying, God ſave His Majeſty. Vpon this, he demanded, Who they were? To which <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Reading</hi> anſwered, in the Name of the reſt, they were Clothiers, and his Loyal Subjects, who would ſtand by him with their Lives and Fortunes againſt all his Enemies. The King hereupon bid them riſe, and demanded what they would ask of him? Vpon this, <hi>Thomas</hi> grew bolder, and ſaid, they had many Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances to offer in behalf of themſelves and their fellow-Subjects, whom the Proud and Covetous Nobility oppreſſed and kept under, to the great hindrance of the flouriſhing of Trade, and of the Kingdom in general, but more particularly to His Majeſty's Coffers, which, if thoſe Lets were removed, would be ſtored with Gold and Silver. To this the King replyed, He heartily thanked them for their minding him of it; but being now upon a haſty Expedition, he muſt refer it to his Return from <hi>Wales;</hi> and ſo Commanding them to draw up their Grievances, and preſent them to him at <hi>London,</hi> he admitted them to kiſs his Hand, and ſo diſmiſſing them at this time, purſued his Iourney, ſaying to a Nobleman that rode near him, I ſee now plainly a Prince may hear and know more out of his Palace, than ever he is able to do in it; for there my Flatterers blind me from ſeeing into Affairs, by laying falſe Perſpectives before me, that they may gain their own Ends and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages on my well-meaning Subjects; but I perceive amongſt plain, down-right Men Truth is much ſooner to be found: And this Evil I will remedy as ſoon as I may, and ſtand in the Defence of them and this Country againſt all Oppoſers, whilſt I am able to wield my Sword, or to the laſt drop of my Blood. And ſo keeping his way, the Clothiers made theirs, with pleaſant Songs, and merry Chear, to <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. How the Clothiers of the VVeſt and North met at <hi>Boſom</hi>'s Inn at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don:</hi> Of the Entertainment they met withal, and the Frolicks they had. How <hi>Cuthbert</hi> fell in Love with his Hoſteſs, and being taken napping by Old <hi>Boſom,</hi> was forced to pay an Hundred Pounds to ſave his Teſticles; with the intrigue of their VVooing, and by what Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem he was catched by the Husband.</head>
               <p>VVHilſt all People were concerned at the Alarm the War threatned from <hi>Normandy</hi> by the Duke, had given this Land, our Iolly Clothiers keeping up their Courage, as being both Wiſe and Valiant,
<pb facs="tcp:172254:4"/> were reſolved not to abate of their wonted Mirth; and having ſeen their Cloth unladed, and lately ſtowed, they went to their uſual Inn, called to this day <hi>Boſom</hi>'s Inn, from a greaſie old ſlovenly Fellow, that firſt built it, and then lived in it, who always went nudging with his Head in his Boſom, in thick furr'd Garments, Winter and Summer, ſo that many in deriſion called him the Emblem or Picture of Old Winter, with Iſicles at his Beard. This Old greaſie Bearward had a Liquoriſh Tooth, he had got a fine handſom Young Wife, who had married him for what he had, but for his Perſon, cared not if he was hanged out of the way, that ſhe might get a Young Husband, to pleaſe her to her heart's content.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of three men in an inn</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Dinner ended, <hi>Tom Dove,</hi> who was ever the merrieſt in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, propoſed to ſing a Song, which was agreed to, and thus he began.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
                  <body>
                     <q>
                        <lg n="1">
                           <head>(1.)</head>
                           <l>VVHen VVinter in his Icy Arms</l>
                           <l>The Earth with Cold does bind,</l>
                           <l>She droops, and cannot ſhew her Charms:</l>
                           <l>But when the Sun, more kind,</l>
                           <l>Aſſiſts her with his warmer heat,</l>
                           <l>O then ſhe ſighs no more,</l>
                           <l>But from the cold Embrace does ſtart,</l>
                           <l>To him ſhe does adore.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="2">
                           <head>(2.)</head>
                           <l>The Roſie bluſh with Lilly mix,</l>
                           <l>And paleneſs put to flight;</l>
                           <l>O there ſhe cou'd for ever fix,</l>
                           <l>For ever take delight.</l>
                           <l>Grey Heads Young Beauties ſo oppreſs,</l>
                           <l>And make them ſigh for change,</l>
                           <l>Excuſe them then, if they tranſgreſs,</l>
                           <l>They have good cauſe to range.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Oh Pox, cries Old <hi>Boſom,</hi> I ſmell a Rat, this is a Banter upon me, becauſe I have marryed a Young Wife, but I'll warrant you I'll watch her Waters ſo narrowly, that I'll keep her from ever a Rabit-ſucker, or Coney-catcher of you all. <hi>Cuthbert</hi> perceiving the Old Blade to be nettled, winked at the reſt, and immediately changed the Diſcourſe to News, ſaying, He had heard that Earl <hi>Morgan</hi> was fled out of the Land, to avoid the King's Diſpleaſure, upon his being diſcovered to ſide with the Duke of <hi>Normandy.</hi> As for him, ſays <hi>Grey,</hi> it's no matter, he was a Covetous Wretch, he uſed to beg Lordſhips and Mannors of the King, and either diſpoſſeſs the Tenants quite, or hold them to Rack-Rents, its well we are rid of him: But my Heart bleeds for the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous and Courteous Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> whom, upon like Suſpicion, the King has baniſhed, ſeized on all he has, turned his poor Lady and Daughter out a begging, who now wander about in a miſerable Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I wiſh I knew where and how to Relieve them.</p>
               <p>Whilſt this Diſcourſe laſted, Drinking, and the noiſe of Fidlers that
<pb facs="tcp:172254:5"/> played without, had lulled Old <hi>Boſom</hi> aſleep, who hanging his Head down, ſnored like a Hog in a Sty. <hi>Cuthbert</hi> took this Opportunity to ſtep into the Kitchen, and make Love to his fine Hoſteſs, admiring ſhe would Marry ſuch a greaſie, Butcherly Beaſt, then gave her a Kiſs, and clapt an Angel into her hand, to buy her a pair of Gloves, pouring out his Amorous Paſſion, and the deſire he had to pleaſe her by Night or Day. At firſt ſhe ſeemed ſhy, as if ſhe underſtood not his meaning, but at laſt told him, ſince ſhe had been ſo unhappy to Marry one ſhe could not love, if he could handſomly contrive the matter, ſhe would grant his Suit. Then he told her, that <hi>Tom Dove</hi> blurting out an unlucky Song, had almoſt made Old <hi>Boſom</hi> jealous, and therefore, to take away all ſuſpicion for the future, ſhe muſt give him leave in her Husband's preſence, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking Offence at it, to rally her, and ſhe ſhew an inveterate hatred, and utter diſlike of him, the better to blind the Old Iealous Coxcomb, that he ſhould not ſuſpect their Love, and they acted it as occaſion offered ſo to the Life, that it ſucceeded for a time to their wiſh; for ſhe often threatned to ſcald him out of the Kitchen, or run him through with the Spit, when he called her Draggle-tail, and dirty Sow, wondring that ſuch an honeſt, grave Man, as her Husband, could find in his heart to love ſuch a dowdy Puſs; ſo that her ſéeming Anger made the Old Man chide her often, for abuſing one of his beſt Gueſts, ſaying, At this rate ſuch a Goſſip as ſhe would ſcare all his Cuſtomers from his Houſe, and then they might both go hang themſelves. However, he had a little Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Tom Dove,</hi> who, to humour the matter, would be Frolickſom, and Ieſt with her, and ſhe would do the like with him. At Night the <hi>London</hi> Merchants came to pay a Viſit to the Clothiers, bringing Wine and Delicacies with them, ſuch as the Inn afforded not; the Glaſſes went round, and they were exceeding merry. But in the height of the Iollity, <hi>Cuthbert</hi> being intent on the Love of his fair Hoſteſs, left them to ſee if he could ſpeak with her in private, and appoint an Aſſignation to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate their Deſires. It was now Twilight, and he perceived her walking at the lower end of the Yard, ſo he ſlily made up to her, and catching her about the Neck, gave her many Amorous Kiſſes; ſhe ſeeing who it was, haſtily retired into a little Shed or Hovel, leading him by the hand; and being entred, ſhutting faſt the Door, gave him a Kiſs, ſaying, Now take your Opportunity, I yield to your Embraces, and tho' the Place be ſomething Incommodious, poor Lovers muſt make a hard ſhift to reap the Fruits of their Deſires.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cuthbert,</hi> who was a Man of Mettle, only replyed with Kiſſes, and immediately fell on board her; but as Ill Luck would have it, the Houſe of Office ſtanding in a corner of this Place, when they were in the height of their Amorous Delight, Old <hi>Boſom,</hi> having ſtuffed his Guts like a
<pb facs="tcp:172254:5"/> Cloak bag, came wallowing to empty his Load, and wondring to find the Door ſhut, being in haſte, rap'd and called out, Who, in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil's Name, is here? Open the Door quickly, or I ſhall diſcharge in my Breeches. The Lovers knowing his hated Voice, were much ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and ſurprized; but there being no Remedy, <hi>Cuthbert</hi> fiercely reply'd It is I, what would you have? None ſhall come in here till I have done my Buſineſs. There are two holes, ſays <hi>Boſom,</hi> and one I think may ſerve your turn. There are ſo, ſays <hi>Cuthbert,</hi> but as it now ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falls out, one is grievouſly beſhit, and I am in the other, therefore ſhift ſomewhere elſe. This ſatisfied him, and immediately he haſled to the Dunghil, and turning up his beaſtly But-end, diſcharged at leaſt half a Peck. As he was retreating from thence, at ſome diſtance he fancied, by the imperfect Light, he eſpyed a Woman ſtep out of the Hovel, and ſlip in at the back door of the Houſe contrary to where he was. This, though he could not charge it certain, with the denyal of Entrance gave him Suſpicion there had been Foul Play; however, he ſeemed to take no notice, till he might be better aſſured: And ſo ſtepping out, he got a Letter to be writ, and carried to his Wife by a Porter, who was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed to tell her, that he brought it from <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> When ſhe read it, ſhe rejoyced, for it imported, that her Husband's Rich Brother lay a Dying, and had ſent for him to watch with him that Night; and in his abſence ſhe doubted not but to have her fill of Pleaſure with <hi>Cuthbert,</hi> though before ſhe had been diſturbed in the midſt of it.</p>
               <p>She ſoon told <hi>Cuthbert</hi> of this, who was overjoyed that ſhe had ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed it ſo eaſily. He no ſooner read the Letter, but called for his Horſe and <hi>Aqua-vitae</hi> Bottle, giving her a Kiſs as in Kindneſs, bidding her be careful of the Houſe, for he was certain he ſhould ſtay all Night, and ſo they parted. Then he carried his Horſe to another Inn, having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſet a Spy upon his Wife, <hi>viz.</hi> the Chamberlain, who would fain have had a lick at her Honey-pot; but ſhe diſdaining him, his Love turned to Envy and Hatred, reſolving none ſhould enjoy, if he could help it, that which himſelf was denyed: He ſate up, watching his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's Return, which he failed not to do when he ſuppoſed his Gueſt and Wife were in bed; and being let in by him, who aſſured him there was a Man in her Chamber, he, enraged with Iealouſie, blundered up ſtairs; his Wife firſt heard him, knowing his tread, and ordered <hi>Cuthbert</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to riſe, and get up the Chimney, and ſtride a croſs the Bar, till ſhe found an Opportunity to further his eſcape to his own Chamber: this he did in ſuch haſt, that he left his Cloaths, but ſhe conveyed them between the Bed and the Mat: By this time <hi>Boſom</hi> entred the Chamber, ſaying, My Dear, I am come ſooner than I thought, for my Brother was only in a Fit, and recovered before I came there. Then peeping
<pb facs="tcp:172254:6"/> under the Bed, as for the Chamber-Pot, he eſpied a Sack-Poſſet, but took no notice of it, ſeeing no body there. Then, made excuſes to look in other Places, and at laſt, peeping ſlightly up the Chimney, ſaw <hi>Cuth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi>'s naked Feet dangling down. The Good Woman fearing a Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, urged him to come to Bed: But he told her, his Horſe had ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and thrown him in a wet Plaſh, and he muſt have a Fire to dry him before he would do it. Immediately calling for Faggots, a Fire was kindled, which as it burnt up, ſmothered and almoſt roaſted <hi>Cuth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> though by the help of his Breath and Piſſing he endeavoured to hinder its Smoak and Heat, ſo that for fear of being marryred, he cryed out lamentably. <hi>Boſom</hi> upon this, peeping up, cryed out, Thieves, Thieves; whereupon his Servants came running up, dragged him down, buffeted him ſeverely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and by <hi>Boſom</hi>'s Order bound him to the Bed poſt. The Good Woman ſeeing him draw his Knife, leaped out of Bed, fell on her Knees, and implored Mercy for him, for it was Mr. <hi>Cuthbert</hi> the Clothier. O then, replyed he, I know his Buſineſs here, and your Cavils were to blind me; however, I'll be merciful, I'll ſpare his Life, but out go his Stones, I'll teach him to Caterwawl with my Wife. And he had certainly done it, had not <hi>Cuthbert</hi> given a Bond of 100 <hi>l.</hi> to releaſe him. His Wife he confined to her Chamber for a Month with Bread and Water, to tool her Letchery, as he ſaid. And this was not done ſo ſecretly, but by the meanes of ſome of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, the other Clothiers came to know of it, which made them laugh heartily, and <hi>Cuthbert</hi> was jeered ever after, for looking Swallows Neſts at ſuch a time of Night in the Chimney, and runnin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the hazard of ſinding his Tail: But he put it off as well as he could.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. How the Clothiers made their Addreſs to the King to Redreſs Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and had their Deſires granted. Of the Merriment they had in their way home. How their Wives hearing what a brave Town <hi>London</hi> was, would needs ſee it: How they were Entertained by the Merchants Wives, and at their Return home longed for fine Cloaths, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>THE Iolly Clothiers having ſold their Cloath to a good Advantage, and received much Money, hearing the King had quieted the <hi>Welſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and was returned to his Palace, remembring what he had ſaid to them, and their Promiſe to attend him, reſolved to be as good as their Words, expecting Advantage thereby from his Grace and Favour, not
<pb facs="tcp:172254:6"/> only for themſelves, but for the People in general. And having drawn up what they thought fit, they ſpruced up themſelves, and went to caſt themſelves at his <hi>Feet,</hi> as hearing in a little time he was to go over the Sea with a great Army againſt <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King, and his Brother <hi>Robert,</hi> thereby to find them Work at home, and prevent their Landing in <hi>England,</hi> and leave the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> Regent at home, they concluded to take the firſt Opportunity, and were ſoon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Preſence.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of king on throne with eight nobles</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The King knowing they were come, placed himſelf in his Royal Robes, with his Nobles about him, making a Glorious Shew, and Commanding them, without fear or favour of any, from the greateſt to the leaſt, boldly and freely to ſpeak what they had to ſay. <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Reading,</hi> who was appointed to ſpeak for them, having made his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty a Preſent of each Man a Hundred Pounds, which amounted to Nine Hundred in all, praying him to accept of it from his Dutiful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, to enable him to def<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the Realm, and carry on the War, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on his Paper, ſaid, We Humbly beſeech Your Majeſty, that there may be a ſettled Meaſure for Cloath throughout the Land, to prevent Differences and Difficulties ariſing in ſeveral Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath-working Towns, by reaſon of the uncertainty of Meaſuring. This ſhall be done, ſaid the King; and thereupon cauſed his own Arm to be meaſured, ſaying,
<pb facs="tcp:172254:7"/> This ſhall be the Standard-meaſure, and ſo I eſtabliſh it, diſannulling all other, as unlawful; and from that time it has been called, the Cloath Yard. Then, becauſe there was a great deal of crack'd Money in the Nation, which many refuſed, and therefore it hindred the Circle of Trade, he deſired, in the Name of his Brethren, that the King would be pleaſed to iſſue out his Royal Proclamation, that it might paſs in Payments without controul. Nay, honeſt Clothiers, replyed the King, I will do better than that; I will Command by my Proclamation none but crack'd Money ſhall go, and then thoſe that have whole Money, will be obliged to track it, and then there will appear no difference.</p>
               <p>The next Demand was, That ſuch as were taken ſtealing their Cloath, when it was on the Tenters in the Fields, might be hanged; for though they were at a vaſt Charge in watching of it, yet little fear of the Puniſhment, which was but a Whipping matter, made Thieves bold, and in great Companies ſet upon thoſe that watched it, and take it by force. To this the King promiſed he would procure ſuch a Law to be made, as ſoon as the Parliament ſitting had diſpatched the weighty Affairs of the Nation, and accordingly it was made; but then Hanging was ſo ſtrange a Death in <hi>England,</hi> that when they took Malefactors, and brought them to the Place of Execution, they could not get a Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man for Money or Entreaty, no, nor by threats of Puniſhment, upon Refuſal; ſo that they were forced to let them go, unleſs they would have hanged them themſelves, which they often did, for fear of incurring the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of the People, by being too cruel to their Fellow-Creatures. But <hi>Hodgkins</hi> loſing much, and being impatient at their Impunity, contrived with a Monk to frame an Engine at <hi>Hallifax</hi> to cut off their Heads with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of a Man; for their Heads were no ſooner in, but a Spring running, upon their touching it, a ſharp Iron bore forcibly down, and whipt them off, and this awed Offenders. But to return: The King, at their Requeſt, forbid Commons to be encloſed by Rich Men, leaving them to the Poor; called Oppreſſors to Account, and puniſhed many of them by Fine and Impriſonment: And then ordered the two Princes his Sons, <hi>viz. William</hi> and <hi>Robert,</hi> to treat the Clothiers ſumptuouſly in his Palace, ſaying, He ſhould from that time eſteem them amongſt the beſt of his Subjects; and ſo they were highly feaſted with Wine, Veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and other Delicacies. But <hi>Simon</hi> of <hi>Southampton,</hi> being a great admirer of Broth, preferred it before all, which made one of the Princes jeſtingly ſay, <hi>Sup,</hi> Simon, <hi>it's very good Broth;</hi> and from thence came the Proverb.</p>
               <p>When they had been well Entertained, to their hearts content, they took their Leave, and rode to the Town, that is now called <hi>Colebrook,</hi> from the Murther of <hi>Cole,</hi> as ſhall be hereafter related. As for their
<pb facs="tcp:172254:7"/> Wains, they were gone before. And here at an Inn they uſually made Merry in their coming and returning from <hi>London:</hi> Nor wanted they the Company of the mens Wives of the Town to bear them Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and be Merry with them, who were ſo extreamly taken with <hi>Tom Dove</hi>'s Merry Pranks, that no ſooner they heard he was come, but they would give their Husbands the ſlip, and run to him like Chickens to a Hen, and in praiſe of him made this Song, which was afterwards ſung all over the Country.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
                  <body>
                     <q>
                        <lg n="1">
                           <head>(1.)</head>
                           <l>Welcome, <hi>Tom Dove,</hi> our only Love,</l>
                           <l>The merrieſt Man alive,</l>
                           <l>Thy Company we do approve,</l>
                           <l>None ſhall us from it drive.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="2">
                           <head>(2.)</head>
                           <l>Though Husbands fret, and pout and ſweat,</l>
                           <l>We care not for't a Pin,</l>
                           <l>They nothing by the ſame ſhall get,</l>
                           <l>For we'll play at In and In.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="3">
                           <head>(3.)</head>
                           <l>Their Jealouſie we do defie,</l>
                           <l>And all their Anger ſcorn,</l>
                           <l>If they our Freedom do deny,</l>
                           <l>We'll graft on them the Horn.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Having continued their Merriment here as long as they thought fit, the Women refuſing to leave their Company, though their Husbands often ſent for them, it was thought fit they ſhould return home, and at <hi>Reading</hi> they parted. Every one arriving at his Houſe, told their Wives how they had been Entertained, and what a fine Town <hi>London</hi> was, which ſet them ſo agog, that they would have no Nay, but ſent Letters, as if they jumped all in a Mind, to meet at <hi>Cole</hi>'s in <hi>Reading,</hi> take his Wife with them, and hey for <hi>London</hi> Town. To all their Husbands diſſwaſions they turned a deaf Ear, thinking a Days, and dreaming a Nights of their pleaſant Iourney, and the Frollicks they expected. So their Husbands finding it in vain, do what they could, to diſſwade them from their headſtrong Humour, gave way to it, and every one had a ſtately Palfrey, and their beſt Apparel, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying Letters of Recommendation to Merchants, to receive, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and ſhew the Bravery of Court and City. And though the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Buſineſs was urgent, that they could not accompany them, they had by Agreement every one a Iourney-man Weaver to ride before them; and ſo with full Purſes to bear their Expences, to <hi>Thomas of Reading</hi>'s they came, who highly feaſted them, and ordering his Wife to Accompany
<pb facs="tcp:172254:8"/> them, to <hi>London</hi> they rode. The Merchants, upon their Arrival, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained them with all the Civility and Treatment imaginable, their Wives accompanyed them to Court, and ſhewed them what was rare to be ſeen; in the City, Shops full of Silks, Stuff, Plate, Iewels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which made them wonder any Place ſhould be ſo Rich, they having never ſeen the like before.</p>
               <p>Whilſt the Merchants Wives thus welcomed the Miſtreſſes, the <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> Weavers in <hi>Candlewick-ſtreet,</hi> then full of them, and <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> did the like by the Iourney-men, plying them with Liquor luſtily, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Wagers were lay'd on both ſides, who worked quickeſt and beſt, ſome of which the Country-men loſt, and ſome the <hi>Londoners.</hi> And ſo having ſeen all of Rarity that the Town could afford, the Merchants Wives preſented the Women with many fine Knacks, and the Merchants ſent Tokens by them to their Husbands. The <hi>London</hi> Weavers preſented the Country Weavers with Merry Songs, Pipes, and Ribbons. So that pleaſed on all hands, they returned wonderfully ſatisfied, and thought the Money in the Iourney well laid out. Yet herein an Inconveniency followed to the Clothiers, for their Wives having ſeen the Gallantry of the City Dames, fell into diſdain of Sheeps Ruſſet, and knowing their Husbands Ability, never left off leading them weary Lives, till they had Cloaths ſent for from <hi>London,</hi> no Argument to the contrary ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying a Pin's Point; nor could any but <hi>London</hi> Taylors ever after that pleaſe them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. How the Good Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury</hi> being baniſhed, his Counteſs and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>air Daughter came to miſerable Poverty, deſpiſed by their own Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants. How <hi>Grey</hi>'s Wife took the Lady <hi>Margaret</hi> into her Service. How the Duke of <hi>Normandy</hi> fell in Love, and attempting to Eſcape with her, had his Eyes put out. How ſhe turned Nun, and was made Abbeſs: With other Matters.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Have already ſpoken ſomething of the Baniſhment of the Good Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> who in his Proſperity was a good Benefactor to the Poor though few in their Diſtreſs would aſſiſt his Counteſs, or Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Margaret</hi> his only Daughter; ſome pretending they durſt not, for f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r of the Kings's Diſpleaſure, others deſpiſing them now fallen from a High Degree to a low Eſtate, as is uſual with Ingrateful People in ſuch Caſes; and thoſe whom they had done moſt for, moſt ſlighted them. So that the ſorrowful Counteſs, worn out with Grief, and pined with
<pb facs="tcp:172254:8"/> Want, died in a Farmer's Out-houſe, who had formerly been her Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, for ſhe was not admitted into the Dwelling-houſe. This great Affliction, in the loſs of ſo dear and tender a Mother, drew Floods of Tears from her fair Daughter's Eyes: She fell upon the dead Body at the homely Grave it was put in, upbraiding Fortune's Fickleneſs, and accuſing the cruel Deſtinies of too much Severity, deſiring them to throw the Earth on her, and bury her with her dear tender Mother, to that they were conſtrained to take her away by force; then falling into a dead<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> they conveyed her to the Farmer's Houſe, and gave her comfort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble things to revive her Spirits, but it ceaſed not her Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. Whereupon the Farmer's Wife, who had ſo often been fed and relieved at the good Earl's Table, and under him had got all they had, ſaid, Carry this puling Baggage out of my Houſe, I wonder what a Murrain you brought her hither to trouble me for. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay, ſaid the Farmer, Wife, let her ſtay here, for though I know ſhe cannot do any hard Work, being brought up renderly, ſhe may do us ſome Service, in keeping our Sheep.</p>
               <p>Theſe Words cut the poor Lady to the Heart, and without ſaying any thing, ſhe went out of the Houſe, reſolving to go to remote Parts of the Country, where none knew her, and truſt in God's Mercy to help her in her Miſery. Blouze, the Farmer's Wife, was glad of her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture; for ſhe being ugly her ſelf, and the young Lady exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eding beautiful, grew jealous of her Husband as ſoon as he ſpoke in her be half, and began to fling and tear like a Fiend of He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. The young La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy having left theſe ungrateful People, put forth her Strength, and though weaker, travelled out of <hi>Shropſhire</hi> into <hi>Glouceſterſhire,</hi> feeding on Berries, and drinking the Waters of clear Springs, till at length, weary and faint, ſhe ſate down upon a Stone by the way ſide, and fell afreſh to lament her hard Fortune; when it chanced ſome young Maidens came by, and ſeeing her in that plight, compaſſionated her, ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Conjectures of the Cauſe; one ſaying, It muſt needs be Love that has brought her into this diſtreſs. Like enough, ſaid another; for I my ſelf was once almoſt at ſuch a paſs, but thank my Stars, I weathered it, and kicked it away with my Heel. Then they began to ask her ſeveral Queſtions, which ſhe anſwered ſo courte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly, that they admired at it, proffering her Victuals and Drink, which they had in their Handkerchiefs and Bottles, for their Day's Subſiſtance, which pinching Hunger conſtrained her to accept; and being refreſhed, her fading Colour returned, and looked in her homely Dreſs (for her rich Ornaments had long before been laid aſide) like a little Angel: At length ſhe demanded whither they were going? They told her, to <hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> Fair, to be hired for Servants; and if ſhe was out of Place, as
<pb facs="tcp:172254:9"/> by her Diſcontent ſhe ſeemed to be, if ſhe would go with them, ſhe might get a good Service, and that if ſhe behaved her ſelf well in it, it might in time prefer her to ſome honeſt Country Fellow for her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. This made her ſmile, and then pauſing a little, thinking it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to live a Servant than wander ſo forlorn up and down, and that in deſart places her Beauty might betray her Modeſty and Chaſtity to the Luſt of ſome brutal Villain, ſhe approved their Counſel, and away they went together.</p>
               <p>Now as ſhe was ſtanding in the Fair, <hi>Grey</hi>'s Wife came to hire Servants, though ſhe had many already, and wiſhfully beholding fair <hi>Margaret</hi>'s modeſt Countenance and behaviour, came to her, and ſaid, Maid, are you willing to be hired? She replied, Yes, good Dame, if you pleaſe, and I ſhall be willing to do any thing I am able or capable of. Well ſaid, replied Dame <hi>Grey;</hi> then, Sweetheart, come along with me; if you are willing, I ſhall be as willing to inſtruct you where you are ignorant; you ſhall be well provided for, and I will give Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Wages to boot.</p>
               <p>Both Parties agreed, ſhe carried her home, and ſet her to carding Wool. <hi>Grey</hi> at Night came from Market, and hearing his Wife had hired a new Servant, ſent for her to ſee her; her Beauty at firſt ſight dazled his Eyes, ſo that he cried out to his Wife, That ſhe had, he thought, brought all the Fair home with her. Why ſo? ſays ſhe. Why, replied he, I never ſaw one fairer in my Life! At this the good Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was nettled, and began to grow jealous, intending in her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's Abſence privately to ſend her away; but after, ſeeing her Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, modeſt Behaviour, and chaſt Carriage, ſhe concluded ſhe could not be tempted to evil, and therefore altered her Reſolution, preferring her above the reſt of her Maids, and tendering her as dear as her own Children.</p>
               <p>Whilſt ſhe ſtayed here, the King had fought a great Battle in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy,</hi> with Duke <hi>Robert</hi> his Brother, taken him Priſoner, and ſeized his Country, and returning, brought him with him, committing him a Priſoner at large to <hi>Cardriff</hi> Caſtle: (for he had liberty with his Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to Hawk. Hunt, and follow other Princely Paſtimes;) when one Day coming to <hi>Glouceſter, Grey</hi> invited him and his Train to a ſplendid Entertainment, and afterward ſhewed him his People at work; when among the Maids the Duke caſting his Eyes on beautiful <hi>Margaret,</hi> ſtood in a maze to ſee ſo fair a Creature in ſuch a place, and fell deſperately in love with her, but concealed it at that time. <hi>Grey</hi>'s Son was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe extreamly enamour'd of her, and indeed every one that ſaw her fell in love with her; but in her low Condition remembring her high Birth, ſhe gave no Countenance to any, till the Duke by Letter, and
<pb facs="tcp:172254:9"/> ſecret Meſſages, made his Love known to her, and after that, often they met in a neighbouring Foreſt, two or three Miles from the Town, and ſhe received from him, with a ſolemn Promiſe of his honourable Love and entire Affection, a Diamond Ring, with many other Princely Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents; and the Deſire ſhe had to ſee her Father, enclined her the ſooner to conſent, for ſhe heard he was in <hi>France,</hi> and the Duke propoſed to ſlip from his Guard in the next Hunting, and meet her in that Foreſt, and convey her thither, where he would marry her in much Princely State: His manly Proportion, Beauty, and Courage, likewiſe fortified her in her Reſolution, to commit her ſelf to his Care and Conduct; and he failed not, at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me appointed, with two truſty Servants, and a Horſe for her to ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> on, to meet her, and ſhe mounted, they poſted away to the Sea-ſide; but no ſhipping being ready to go off, they waited ſo long, that the Noiſe of his Eſcape being brought to the King's Ear, ſuch ſtrict Search was made, that he was found, and the fair Lady in his company: But ſetting himſelf before her, he drew his Sword, and ſternly commanded his Purſuers not to advance a Step, for if they did, they muſt come on the point of it; but they being a multitude, in hopes of Reward preſſed forward to ſeize him, when the Duke ſo layed man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully about him, that nine or ten of them were ſlain, the reſt beat off, many wounded, with a Cry raiſing the whole Country, his Servants ſlain in his Defence, he at laſt with the beautious <hi>Margaret,</hi> was taken Priſoner, and both carried back to <hi>Cardiff</hi> Caſtle, till the King's Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſhould be put out with Burning-glaſſes, and the Maid which he believed had enticed him to eſcape, ſhould be put to death by ſtrangling. This cruel Sentence being noiſed abroad, <hi>Grey</hi>'s Wife underſtood that it was her dear <hi>Margaret</hi> that was doomed to die, whoſe Abſence ſhe had mourned ever ſince ſhe was miſſing. This brought her almoſt to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction; but taking more ſober Advice, ſhe for a good Summ got the Execution of the Sentence on both delayed, and writing to all the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiers Wives to haſt to <hi>London,</hi> and meet her there, letting them know the Occaſion; they failed not to do it, and going in their richeſt Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel to the Palace, falling at the King's Feet, <hi>Grey</hi>'s Wife ſhedding abundance of Tears, humbly beſought His Highneſs to ſpare the Life of her poor innocent Maid whom the Love of the Duke his Brother had cauſed to fall under his Diſpleaſure, and by him to be ſentenced to death, The King upon this demanded who they were? and when he underſtood they were the Clothiers Wives, he bid them ſtand up, and asking them many Queſtions, hearing what a vertuous beautiful Maid ſhe was, he was moved with Compaſſion towards her, and granted her Pardon, for Life and Liberty, but would in no wiſe do it for the Duke, fearing at
<pb facs="tcp:172254:10"/> one time or other he might effectually eſcape and raiſe fierce Wars a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and withal ſtrictly commanded that the Maid for her Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption ſhould be puniſhed by ſeeing his Eyes put out.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Grey</hi>'s Wife humbly thanked the King, and returning with joy, cauſed fair <hi>Margaret</hi> to be releaſed; but when ſhe underſtood the Duke's Puniſhment was not remitted, and that ſhe muſt be a Spectator of ſo killing a Sight, her Love to him made her burſt into Tears, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately wiſh that the putting out her own Eyes might excuſe him, ſince they had been criminal in leading him to do what he did; but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing availed, for ſhe was compelled to be at the woful Sight, but before it was done, they embraced, kiſſed, and tenderl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mourned, weeping over one another, ſo that the Hearts of thoſe that ſtood by melted at their paſſionate Grief.</p>
               <p>The Duke, of a haughty Spirit, enraged to be thus dealt withal by his Brother, for Grief and Anger beat his Brains our againſt the Walls of the Caſtle wherein he was cloſe confined, and ſo died; which woful Tragedy fair <hi>Margaret</hi> no ſooner heard of, but burſting into a flood of Tears, ſhe diſcovered to <hi>Grey</hi> and his Wife, her Parentage, and the Miſeries of her younger Years, at which they greatly wondred; and now becoming weary of the World, ſhe vowed a Religious Life, went into a Nunnery, and for her vertuous Behaviour, was in time made Abbeſs, and ſpending her Days in Devotion, died an honourable Virgin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. How a Law was made to Arreſt Men for Debt, and how difficult it was to get Officers, no <hi>Engliſh</hi> being then found that would accept of the Place. How <hi>Tom. Dove</hi> was Arreſted, and how <hi>Gerrard</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Officers. How <hi>Tom. Dove</hi> falling into Poverty, was ſighted by his Servants, and others. How in his Deſpair the Clothiers fet him up again, ſo that he became very Rich, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the Reign of this King <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, Arreſting and Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men for Debt was firſt eſtabliſhed by Act of Parliament, taken from a Cuſtom uſed among the <hi>Flemings;</hi> before, their Goods being on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeizable, and their Perſons free to labour and get more for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of themſelves and Family; and however Creditable it is eſteemed now amongſt the Catchpoles, who make great Intereſt, and give good Summs of Money for their Places, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men in thoſe Days ſo abhorred the Thoughts of thruſting their fellow-Subjects into Priſons, to reſtrain that Liberty which all things in Nature ſo much deſire, and let them lie ſtarving between Stone Walls, as too cruelly now it is ſeen, that it was as hard for the Sheriffs to get Catchpoles, as <hi>Hodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> of <hi>Hallifax</hi> Hangmen, no <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man being to be found, though
<pb facs="tcp:172254:10"/> never ſo poor, that for any Money would take that deſpiſed Office upon him, ſo that they were obliged to ſend for <hi>Flemings,</hi> maintain them a Table, and give them large Sallaries.</p>
               <p>Soon after this Law was made, <hi>Tom. Dove</hi> received great Loſſes by the Merchants Goods being taken on the Seas, whilſt <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England</hi> were at Wars, and coming up to Town to ſee if he could get in any Debts, the two Catchpoles, <hi>Flemings,</hi> hired by the Sheriffs of <hi>London</hi> to do the Office, were ſet on by his Creditors to ſeize him, and being ſhowed him in the Street, after the Faſhion of their Country, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming behind him with their Maces, firſt knocked him down, and then bid him ſtand, and charged him with Arreſt. This ſtartled him, and ſpoiled his Mirth; the thing was ſo unuſual, that he knew not what to make of it, but thinking they deſigned to rob him, cried out, Thieves; ſo that a great Crowd got about them, and they had been knocked on the Head, had not the Creditors came in and told the Cauſe, and being known Citizens, pacified the Multitude. However, going into a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, <hi>Tom Dove</hi> ſent for <hi>Gerrard</hi> of <hi>Gerrard</hi>'s-<hi>Hall,</hi> where he had ſome Effects lying, to come and bail him, and he accordingly came, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to be his Bail, affirming him to be a very honeſt Man, and though Fortune had now ſhewed him a ſlippery Trick, to trip up his Heels, ſhe would no doubt in a little time be more favourable, and raiſe him again. Then they demanded a Groat as their Fee, when but Two Pence was their due, or elſe (they ſwore) they would not take his Bail, but to Goal <hi>Tom. Dove</hi> muſt go. Hah! (ſaid <hi>Gerrard,</hi> frowning on them) do you come hither to do Iuſtice, and by Extortion would break our Laws: To this they inſtantly replied, They would do as they liſt, for the Law was in their hands. Then looking on <hi>Dove,</hi> and ſeeing the Blood tric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle down his Forehead, he demanded how it came, or who had dared to abuſe him. Why, ſaid <hi>Dove,</hi> theſe two Varlets knocked me down, without a Word ſpeaking, and broke my Head. Nay then; ſaid he, flauderkins if you are ſo inſolent in this City, 'tis time to chaſtize <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u, and not let you reign in your roguery, to abuſe honeſt Men. Why, replied they, it is the Cuſtom of our Country. What, ſaid he, to be Rogues? Nay, then I'll ſhew you the Cuſtom of ours, and how we ſerve them. Then in his two mighty Paws he ſeized them, and in vain ſtrugling, flung them on his Back, as if they had been little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, carried them to the next Horſe-Pond, and douced them over Head and Ears ſo long, till they were almoſt drowned, then turned them looſe to the Rabble, who worry'd and kick'd them about like Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balls. Being got clear, they ſneaked away into their own Country, and gave ſuch an Account of their Vſage, that it was ſome Years before any <hi>Flemings</hi> could be perſwaded to come over again to do this Office;
<pb facs="tcp:172254:11"/> nay in ſome Towns they were knocked on the Head in attempting to Arreſt Men, and were ſo generally hated of the People, that they were as Egyptian Locuſt and Plague of the Nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tom. Dove</hi> was not idle all this while, but made his Eſcape, left <hi>London,</hi> and went home; but b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nging little Money, his Servants, who were moſtly Poor Mens Children, that he had taken from the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and brought up from their Infancies, at his own Charge, firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to murmur for their Wages; and though he gave every one as far as his Money would go, leaving himſelf not a Farthing, they unkindly forſook him, notwithſtanding his paſſionate Intreaties and Beſeechings, with Tears in his Eyes, that they would not leave him in his Diſtreſs, utterly to undo him by leaving his Work half undone.</p>
               <p>But the Clothiers hearing of his Misfortune, and pitying him, ſent a collected Summ of 800 l. with part of which he pay'd his Debts, and employ'd the Overplus in carrying on his Trade, receiving again his ingrateful Servants, upon their Repentace. He became very Fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, grew very Rich, marry'd his Three Daughters with great Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to Knights, built Alms-houſes, and died full of Years, beloved by all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. How the Clothiers aſſiſted the King in his Wars with Men and Money, by which means he won great Victories, and compell'd the <hi>French</hi> King to a Peace. How on his Return he made a Progreſs to viſit them, and of his Entertainment, to his great Content.</head>
               <p>KIng <hi>Henry</hi> being in Wars againſt <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King, and hard put to it for Men and Money in another Country, the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiers in reſpect of what Kindneſs he had done them, and for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>England,</hi> reſolved to raiſe a great Stock of Money, and with the Leave of the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> who governed the Realm in the King's Abſence. Five thouſand Men, cloathing them in white Coats li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d with red, and arming them compleatly, ſent them over, and Ten thouſand Pounds, to the King, to enable him to maintain his Forces. The King ſeeing this, highly commended the Clothiers of <hi>England,</hi> ſaying, Never Prince had better Subjects. With this Auxilary Force he won many Battles and Towns, till the <hi>French</hi> King, tired out, was conſtrained to make Peace, allowing our King all the Charges he had been at in the Wars, vowing never to aſſiſt his Rebels, and not to moleſt him in any thing he was now in Poſſeſſion of. So having ſetled his Affairs in <hi>Normandy,</hi> and the Frontiers, he returned in triumph, and as the firſt Mark of his Favour, made the Cloathworkers a Copora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, endowing them with large Privileges, beſtowing many Mannor-Houſes on them, as proper Places to ſet the Poor on work for their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage,
<pb facs="tcp:172254:11"/> and Peace firmly ſettled, he reſolved to viſit thoſe, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them with his Princely Preſence, that had been ſo kind to him in his need.</p>
               <p>Spring come, he ſet forward with a Princely Train, and the firſt Viſit was made to <hi>Thomas of Reading,</hi> who knowing before hand of his coming, made ſuitable Preparations, Feaſting him as Richly as if he had been in his own Palace: For the King being brought into a great Hall, found four long Tables ready covered; and paſſing through that Place, he came into a fair large Parlour hung with Tapeſtry, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woven with curious Devices in Gold, Silver, and Silk, where a Table was prepared for his Highneſs; all the Floor was covered with fine Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Cloath, which after Dinner was diſtributed amongſt His Majeſty's Attendants. The King being ſate, and the chiefeſt Nobility, a delicate Banquet was ſerved up in Plate, and after that, Sweetmeats and Fruit in Glaſs Veſſels curiouſly wrought; Wine went freely about, and the Attendants were very numerous. In the Hall dined the King's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, attended on by the Apprentices of the Houſe, and all ſounded with Melodius Muſick. Cedar-wood, and other Perfuming Woods were burnt to make a fragrant ſmell. After Dinner the King went to ſee the Work-houſes, where the Cloath was prepared and made; in one he found Fifty Looms, and Men at Work in them merrily ſinging; in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 100 Wheels, with Maids a ſpinning at them; in another 100 Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Wool, in another 150 Poor Mens Children picking the Wool, for which they had two Pence a Day and their Victuals; in another 50 Sheer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men, in another as many Dyers, and in the next, Trullers; which great number of People the King wondred how he could maintain out of one Trade; and at his departure he was preſented with a fair Golden Cup, emboſſed with many Devices relating to the Cloath-working Trade, which he ever uſed at his Table afterward: And for this great Kindneſs he built an Abby in the Town, and a fair Caſtle, made <hi>Cole</hi> Governour of <hi>Reading,</hi> and when he died, himſelf was buried in the Abby, keeping his Reſidence often in the Caſtle, ſaying, he could be no where better than among ſuch good Neighbours.</p>
               <p>When the King had made his Progreſs to viſit all the Clothiers, he returned home highly ſatisfied with the Entertainment he had received, and in <hi>London</hi> builded Places where they ſhould bring and lay up their Cloath for Sale, to be viewed on certain days, prohibiting Stuffs and Silks to be brought from Foreign Parts; and enjoyning his Subjects to follow his Example, in wearing Cloath Garments; ſo that the Woollen Manufacture grew not only Profitable, but Famous through all the World, And this Iſland by Strangers was called the <hi>Colchos,</hi> or <hi>Heſperian</hi> Land, from whence the Golden Fleeces were brought, to cloath and keep
<pb facs="tcp:172254:12"/> warm Mankind againſt the nipping Cold, and Rage of Winter Storms, and the Drapers then firſt began to Trade in Woollen Cloth, ſeeing it a very profitable way; for before, the Clothiers ſold what was uſed in <hi>England</hi> themſelves, for the proper uſe of the Natives, and Strangers, in their Apparel, in whole Pieces or Remnants, and had Stalls and Stands for that purpoſe; for the Merchants were under an Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not to ſell any here, but what they bought was to be tranſported beyond the Seas.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. How <hi>Thomas of Reading,</hi> at the <hi>Crane</hi> Inn, at <hi>Colebrook,</hi> in his Return from <hi>London</hi> with a great Charge of Money, being in Bed, was let down by a Trap-door into a Scalding Cauldron, and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered. Of the ſad Omens that preceded it. How the Murther was found out, the Hoſt and Hoſteſs hanged, and their Houſe burnt down. Of his ſumptuous Funeral in the Abby of <hi>Reading,</hi> the Monument the King cauſed to be erected, and his Epitaph.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THomas of Reading,</hi> frequently coming to <hi>London</hi> on his Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, uſed in his way to call at <hi>Colebrook,</hi> (ſince ſo named by his unhappy End, but) then only <hi>Brook Town,</hi> from a little Brook running by it into a River that carried the Water into the <hi>Thames,</hi> and his Inn was uſually at the <hi>Crane,</hi> where, when he firſt came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, lived an aged Couple of very honeſt People; but in concluſion, they dying, a villainous Fellow who had been Tapſter with them for a time, though formerly a Soldier in the <hi>French</hi> Wars, prevailed with the old Peoples Daughter, who was a little ſilly, and married her; by which means he got his Head into the Houſe, but (as it was afterwards found out) having a Wife alive, though it was kept ſecret, the poor Girl was ſoon ſuſpected to die of Poyſon, and his other Wife, as if he had newly married, and brought her from the Northern Parts, was introduced, and being a cunning Iade, ſhe knew the way ſo to wheedle, coaks, and flatter her Gueſt, that they took her for a ſharp, induſtrious Woman; ſo that <hi>Thomas of Reading</hi> often talking to her, was taken with her Diſcourſe, and would lie now and than in the Houſe, as he returned late from <hi>London,</hi> though in the end it proved his Ruine, as will hereafter appear.</p>
               <p>Theſe People, it ſeems, though to appearance they had a good Trade, yet being wicked, God blaſted their Endeavours; ſo that fretting in their Minds, they fell to contriving how to be Rich, but could find Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in nothing. At laſt the Wife contrived the Death of <hi>Thomas of Reading,</hi> after a wicked manner, imparting the Bloody Deſign to her Husband, who (tho' Villainous enough) was not willing to give Conſent
<pb facs="tcp:172254:12"/> thereto, uſing Arguments to diſſwade her, as the Danger of their Lives, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But ſhe ſlighted what he ſaid, and told him it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible it ſhould be diſcover'd, as ſhe would manage it; ſo that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding how ſhe had laid the Plot, by her Perſwaſions, and tempted with the Thoughts of great Gain, he promiſed to be Aſſiſtant therein.</p>
               <p>In a little time after, <hi>Thomas of Reading</hi> called here, in his way to <hi>London,</hi> and order'd a Supper to be got ready againſt his Return at Night. Having diſpatch'd his Buſineſs at <hi>London,</hi> he returned with Two Hundred Pound he had received of the Merchants; but by the way, met with many ill Omens of his Death: For his Horſe floun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd in a ſtiff, clayey Slough, and ſtriving to get him out, ſlipp'd his Shoulder, ſo that he was forc'd to leave him in the next Village, and hire another. When he came near <hi>Colebrook,</hi> his Noſe fell a bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, unuſually, and he grew very ſad, more-eſpecially when he met with Ravens that flew accroſs and ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut him, croaking diſmally. Coming to the Inn, he ſate him down, and by the Heavineſs and Melancholly that had ſeiz'd his Spirits, look'd very much concern'd; which made the Hoſt and Hoſteſs ask how he did, and why he was ſo dull? To whom he reply'd, I know not; but the Signs I have obſerv'd, and the ſecret Impulſes of my Heart, gives me to think I have not long to live, therefore I would fain reach home to make my Will, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare my ſelf to leave the World. His ſaying this, made them ſuſpect he had divined their Bloody Purpoſes.</p>
               <p>However, to be ſhort, he was perſwaded by ſome Arguments they us'd, to ſtay all Night, (only he writ a Letter to his Wife, to inform her of it, and where to find him if he came not by ſuch a time,) and ſo gave his Enemies an Opportunity to facilitate their Ends: For finding himſelf drouſie, he deſired to go to Bed, and was ſhewed into the Fatal Chamber, where he read for ſome time, when a Schreech Owl came beating her boding Wings againſt the Window ſeveral times, with horrid Cries, and the Night Raven ſate croaking on a Tree hard by. Bleſs me! ſaid he, what can all theſe Preſages of Death mean, but that I have not long to live? and ſo he went to Prayers a good while, and then to Bed. The Hoſteſs liſtned at the Door, till ſhe perceived he was aſleep; and the Gueſt being all gone out of the Houſe, ſhe ran down to her Husband, and told him that now was the only time; and both together effected his unhappy Death after this manner. A Trap-door being made underneath his Bed, which was in a Room over a great Cauldron, they had nailed the Bed-cloaths to the further ſide of the Bed, to the Bedſtead; ſo that now opening the Trap-door, he was ſhot into the Cauldron of ſcalding Water underneath, waking in his Fall, and crying, The Lord have Mercy on my Soul. Theſe were his laſt Words,
<pb facs="tcp:172254:13"/> for ſoon he was ſtifled and ſcalded to Death, then with Pull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ys having drawn the Trap-door up again, they drew him out, when dead, with an Iron Hook, ſtripping him, took his Money, and at a back Window threw the dead Body into the Brook; but as Providence order'd it, it was not carry'd away, but ſtopped near the Houſe by a Tuft of Withes, and found the next Morning by ſome Fiſhermen, but who it was they knew not, till <hi>Cole</hi>'s Wife came about Noon, and her Man with her, asking for her Husband; they denied he had been there, but ſhe ſhewing them the Letter they were ſtartled, and hearing of a dead Body in the Brook ſhe went to ſee it, and finding it her dear Husband, fell upon it and embrac'd it with Quteries, and a Flood of Tears; then ſearch was made for his Horſe, which being found in the Stable, the Hoſt, ſtruck with the Horror of the Guilt, fled, but the Hoſteſs was taken and charged with the Murther, which upon ſtrict Examination ſhe confeſſed, and that they had ſerved ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſo. Soon after her Husband was ſeized by Hue-and Cry at <hi>VVin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> and both of them deſervedly hanged, making a long Confeſſion of their wicked Lives, too tedious hear to be ſet down.</p>
               <p>The Body of <hi>Cole</hi> was Embalmed, and notice ſent to the Clothiers to come to his Funeral, who, very ſorrowful at the News, failed not. The King hearing of this Diſaſter, proteſted he had loſt one of the beſt Subjects in his Kingdom, ordering the Inn to be conſumed with Fire, and laying a heavy Curſe upon any that ſhould hereafter rebuild it, orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Town, from the Body's being found in the Brook, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be called <hi>Colebrook,</hi> which Name it retains to this Day: He was bury'd with all the ſolemn Pomp imaginable at the King's new-founded Abby at <hi>Reading,</hi> and the King was at the charge of a Stately Monument, with this Epitaph.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="epitaph">
                  <body>
                     <q>
                        <l>HEre lies the worthy Clothier of the Weſt,</l>
                        <l>Whom God with Wealth and Honeſty had bleſt,</l>
                        <l>By murthering Hands the guiltleſs good Man dy'd,</l>
                        <l>Belov'd he was, and was his Country's Pride;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Reading</hi> ne'er boaſted ſuch a Man as he,</l>
                        <l>But here his Duſt lies to Eternity.</l>
                     </q>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>As for the reſt of the Clothiers they flouriſhed many Years, got great Eſtates, and laid a Foundation for many Noble and Worſhipful Familes, being in muſt Eſteem, and deſcending to the Grave full of Years, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir Deaths lamented by Rich and Poor.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> 
               <hi>And thus having given as large an Account of the Lives and Actions of</hi> The Six Worthy Yeomen of the Weſt, <hi>as our intended Brevity would permit, I refer you to the Hiſtory more at large, ſold by</hi> I Deacon <hi>at the</hi> Angel <hi>in</hi> Grit-ſpur-ſtreet, <hi>without</hi> Newgate.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
